Those who assist in the chanting of Buddhist scriptures believe
những người mà đi trợ niệm thì đang có
that the deceased's body softens, their skin becomes rosy, and
kiến thức là người mềm ra rẻ hồng hào
that this is a sign of rebirth in the Pure Land. Chanting Buddhist scriptures in a
cho đó là vãng sinh niệm phật ở trong
Dharma assembly or chanting has
pháp hội hay là tụng kinh nó có công
its power, but that power does not guarantee
năng của nó nhưng không phải cái công
rebirth. Therefore,
năng đó là công năng được vãng sinh nên
we should not deceive ourselves.
chúng ta đừng tự lừa dối mình mà chúng
We must have practical knowledge and
ta phải có cái kiến thức thực tế trải
experience, and when we hear something, we must think
nghiệm và khi nghe cái gì phải tư duy rõ
clearly. This is a question I respectfully ask the Venerable Master regarding the
ràng đó là câu hỏi bạch Cô chỉ dạy à
phenomena that occur with the recently deceased and
hiện tượng xảy ra với người mới mất và
how to properly encourage Buddhist followers. I respectfully
cách sách tấn phật tử đúng pháp em Kính
request the Venerable Master's guidance. Recently, the family of
bạch cô chủ nhiệm vừa qua gia đình Phật
Buddhist follower Hang had a relative, her father-in-law, pass away.
tử Hằng có người thân là bố chồng bỏ báo
When he passed away, Buddhist followers
thân khi ông bỏ báo thân có các phật tử
from other temples came to assist in the
ở chùa khác đến trợ
chanting of "Nam Mô A Di Đà Phật" for
niệm chỉ Niệm Nam Mô A Di Đà Phật trong
over 7 hours. Buddhist follower Hang shared
thời gian hơn 7 giờ phật tử hàng chia sẻ
that the following phenomena occurred: the entire body became
có những hiện tượng như sau toàn thân
very soft, the skin remained rosy, not
người rất mềm da rẻ vẫn hồng hào không
stiff or discolored as usual. The
bị cứng và biến sắc như thông thường khi
death was very peaceful and serene. The
mất cũng rất nhẹ nhàng thanh thản con
deceased's daughter saw a
gái của người mất nhìn thấy trong phòng
bright yellow light in the room. The
có ánh sáng vàng rực Có Phật a di đà
deceased was very joyful and followed the
hiện xuống người mất rất hoan hỉ đi theo
Buddha without any attachment to the
Phật a di đà mà không hề quyến luyến gia
family, not looking back at his wife or children. I respectfully request...  I
đình không nhìn lại vợ con em Xin thành
respectfully request guidance from the head teacher on the following matters:
kính mong cô chủ nhiệm chỉ dạy các việc
Firstly, is it
ý thứ nhất
due to the
sắc thân thể không bị cứng là do công
merit of chanting and reciting the Buddha's name
đức của việc trợ niệm trì danh hiệu phật
during the deceased's peaceful passing, without any change in expression or stiffness in the body, due to the merit of the chanting and recitation of the Buddha's name, or due to the deceased's
hay do bản thân người mất khi còn tại
diligent practice, enlightenment, and practice of giving, doing good deeds, and offering to the Three
Thường thực hành bố thí Hành Thiện cúng
Jewels while alive, with unwavering devotion and reliance on the Three Jewels to seek
ạ Kính thưa các quý đạo hữu về cái phần
rebirth in the Western Pure Land? Or is it due to both factors? Dear fellow practitioners, regarding the soft, rosy complexion of the deceased's body, which I have already shared, today I will give another example to make it easier for you to understand and more realistically relate to life. In
đạo hữu dễ hiểu hơn xát thực hơn với đời
the previous article, I
được cái bài lần trước thì tâm chếu hoàn
answered that after death, the human body, at the moment of death, is in
quán có trả lời rằng cơ thể của con
pain like a turtle having its shell pulled out alive. The pain of a turtle having its
thân cơ thể đau như rùa bị rút mai sống
shell pulled out alive is the
tức là con rùa nó bị rút mai sống nó đau
same pain a dying person experiences. I have
vậy nó đau như vậy và tâm chiếu Hoàn
experienced this firsthand.
quán đã trải nghiệm việc này đã trải
Then, the Buddha's words are
nghiệm được việc này rồi thì lời Phật là
absolutely certain; no one can speak
chắc thực không ai có có thể mà nói
more accurately than the Buddha. As for the
chính xác hơn bằng Phật được thế còn cái
reaction that allows us to perceive
phản ứng để chúng ta nhìn thấy cái hiện
pain, it doesn't depend
tượng đau hay không nó không phụ thuộc
on whether the deceased is experiencing pain or not.
vào người chết có bị đau hay không Vì
Why? Because when a person
sao Vì khi người ta
dies, it's like someone who is in so much pain
chết giống như cái người mà bị đau quá
that they lose all sensation. They
mà mất hết cảm giác ấy thì cái người đấy
can't struggle, they don't know
cũng Không giãy dụa được cũng không biết
what pain is anymore. Have you
đâu là đau nữa các quý Đạo Hữu đã bao
ever meditated and had your legs go numb?
giờ ngồi thiền mà hai chân nó bị tê cứng
At that time, did your legs feel
chưa lúc đấy chân các quý Đạo Hữu có cảm
anything? So, when a deceased person lies
không cho nên khi cái người chết ấy nằm
on the bed with their limbs numb,
ở trên giường rồi tay chân đã như vậy
if they were in pain, there
rồi thì nếu người đấy có bị đau thì là
would be a physical reaction beforehand.
lúc trước sẽ có phản ứng của cơ thể
But when the pain becomes too intense, the nerves become paralyzed, and
nhưng đến lúc nó đau quá nó bị tê liệt
then they become completely still. They might
thần kinh rồi thì lúc bấy giờ sẽ làm im
even lose all
Thiên thít và nó lại còn không có cả
outward reactions. For example, at
những cái phản ứng ra ngoài có TH lúc
first, their breathing might be very heavy, but
đầu là thở hồng học rất mạnh nhưng về
later it will become lighter. That's
sau Hơi Thở nó sẽ nhẹ dần đi Cái đấy là
perfectly normal. When someone is in such pain, the
rất bình thường thì khi mà nó bị đau như
entire body, including the muscles,
thế thì toàn thân cơ thể là các cái khối
contracts, but it doesn't
cơ nó bị co rút nhưng nó lại không thể
manifest outwardly.  A doctor would
hiện ra ngoài việc này bác sĩ thì sẽ
know better because the mind-body-controlling practitioner,
biết rõ hơn ạ bởi vì tâm chiếu Hoàn quán
having
đã trải
undergone three death simulations,
qua ba lần chết thử trên tâm chiếu Hoàn
sits in a normal sitting position,
quán ngồi ở tư thế ngồi bình thường
not doing anything, yet the entire body
không hề làm nhưng toàn bộ trong thân nó
is constricted, suffocated, muscles
là một sự bóp chặt Bóp nghẹt cơ nó cứng
completely stiff, tongue retracts, ears cannot
hoàn toàn lưỡi nó thụt vào tai nó không
hear—meaning there is no
nghe thấy tức là nó không còn một cử
movement at all. This is outwardly apparent, so
động gì Thể hiện ra bên ngoài cho nên
outsiders perceive the
người ngoài nhìn vào như vậy tưởng rằng
person as peaceful, unharmed, and
người đó đang bình an vô sự không đau
painless. Therefore, it cannot be seen with the naked eye,
đớn cho nên không thể nhìn bằng cái mắt
but through
của mình được mà phải bằng sự trải
experience, and perhaps with some kind of machine.
nghiệm và có thể nếu có cái bộ máy nào
If someone is brought in at the moment of death,
đó Nếu ai lúc chết mà được đưa vào thì
we can see the
chúng ta sẽ nhìn thấy những cái hoạt
bodily functions
động trên cơ thể bằng những cái điện tâm
clearly through electrocardiograms. So, it's not that the person is still because they are
đồ thì rất là rõ Cho nên không phải là
not in pain, but
người ta làm im là người ta không đau mà
because they cannot lift their arms or legs.
do không thể nhấc tay Nhấc chân lên nữa
For example, the mind-controlling practitioner says this
rồi ví dụ tâm chế Hoàn quán nói thế này
to show respect: If someone has a paralyzed arm and
để cho có quý đạo ữu cái người bị bại
cannot lift it,
tay mà không Giơ được lên ấy ở trong tay
does it hurt? If it does, they nod their head. Because if
không có đau thì gật đầu bởi vì cái
someone has a paralyzed arm and cannot
người bị bị bại tay mà không nhấc được
lift it, does it hurt?  It was very painful, and the hands were very
lên ấ có đ đ không ạ rất đau mà tay rất
stiff, but they couldn't lift them.
co cứng nhưng mà lại không Giơ được lên
So, when a person dies, they remain still
cho nên cái người lúc chết là họ làm yên
like that, their whole body has no
như thế rồi toàn thân họ không còn sức
strength left to tense, pull, or move their arms and
lực để gồng để kéo để cử động được tay
legs, but they are still in great pain. Having just
chân nhưng trong người cũng rất là đau
died, they have just gone through a
vừa mới chết xong thì họ đã vừa trải qua
whole ordeal of movement and pain,
cả một vấn đề mà nó bị vận động bị đau
like a turtle withdrawing into its shell.
như là rùa rút mai sống như thế rồi thì
When they die, all those
khi chết đi thì toàn bộ cái khối cơ đó
muscles begin to
nó bắt đầu làm cho cơ thể con người cứng
stiffen, and after a certain time, they naturally relax
lên cứng lên và đến một thời gian nào đó
because the body is no longer moving. The relaxation time
ra vì cơ thể chúng ta không vận động nữa
depends on
rồi cho nên nó tự mềm ra thì tùy theo
the intensity of the pain. If the pain is less, the
cái sức đau của mỗi người nếu đau ít thì
stiffness is less, and the relaxation is faster. If the pain is more, the
co cứng ít độ mềm ra nhanh Nếu đau nhiều
stiffness is more, and the relaxation takes
thì co cứng nhiều và độ mềm ra thời gian
longer. Therefore, some funeral assistance sessions require
nó dài hơn cho nên có những đám trợ niệm
8 hours of
Người ta bảo tôi trợ đệm 8 tiếng có
assistance, some 24 hours, and some even
những đám trợ liệm trợ niệm 24 tiếng có
over 30 hours before it's considered
những đám trợ liệm hơn 30 tiếng mới bảo
successful because only then does the body
là thành công vì lúc đấy nó mới
soften. This depends on the level of pain a person experiences
mềm đó là do cái đau của con người ta
before death.  It will be
thế nào trước lúc chết thì sau đó nó sẽ
hard, but then it will soften to a
cứng nhưng rồi nó sẽ mềm ở một mức độ
certain extent. And this skin of ours,
đó thế và cái lớp da của mình này này nó
at a certain point, because the blood and
đến một độ nào đó thì vì máu nó không
water stop circulating, it becomes plump and moist.
lưu thông nước nó không lưu thông nữa
We see the skin become firm and
Nhuận ra thì chúng ta thấy da nó căng
beautiful. This is what the mind-body contemplation says,
đẹp đẽ rất đẹp tâm chiếu hoản quán nói
dear fellow practitioners. Do you agree with this? When blood stops circulating,
như thế các quý đạo hữu Tư duy có thấy
water starts to accumulate under the skin,
dưới cái lớp da này nước nó bắt đầu ứ
making it plump and
vào thì nó bắt đầu là nó căng mọng nên
beautiful. At that time, those assisting with the chanting will
đẹp thì lúc đó những người trợ niệm thì
say, "What a beautiful appearance! That's rebirth!"
nói rằng là tướng đẹp quá đấy là vãng
All those
sinh rồi thì toàn bộ những người mà đi
assisting with the chanting, with their knowledge, see that the person's skin is
trợ niệm thì đang có kiến thức là người
soft and rosy, and they consider that to be rebirth.
mềm da dẻ hồng hào cho đó là vãng sinh
Now, let's take the mind-body contemplation as an example.
bây giờ tâm chiếu Hoàn quán lấy ví dụ
Consider a fish.
Xem xem con cá nó có vãng sinh
A fish that has just died is
không một con cá nó vừa mới chết xong
very soft. Then it becomes hard
thì nó rất là mềm xong sau nó có cứng
again, dear
lại không quý đạo
practitioners. But at a certain point, does the
hữu Nhưng đến một thời điểm nào đó con
fish soften? It softens, but
cá đấy nó có mềm ra không mềm ra nhưng
it's not rotten, it's not spoiled, it still has the
nó chưa ươn nó chưa thối nó vẫn có mùi
fragrant smell of a fish, right? But at a certain
thơm của con cá phải không Nhưng đến một
point...  It only starts to rot when it starts to smell
độ nào đó nó mới thối ra nó mới có mùi
rotten. Is there any dead fish that stays stiff from the
ươn Thế có con cá chết nào mà nó cứng từ
moment it dies until it rots?
lúc đấy đến lúc thối ra
It's a biological body, and so is a
không Nó là một cơ thể sinh học và con
human being. After death,
người ta cũng thế chết rồi thì mới chết
it becomes soft, then it hardens, and if left for a long time,
thì mềm sau rồi thì sao thì cứng cứng để
it becomes soft again. So, does a fish that softens have been reborn? Therefore,
ra như thế nó có vãng sinh không cho nên
we shouldn't base our judgment on whether the body is soft
chúng ta không căn cứ vào cơ thể mềm
or hard, or whether it's
cứng và không căn cứ vào cơ thể lại có
moist or not. Because when a fish
nhuận nước hay không vì cái con cái lúc
hardens, then softens,
nó cứng lên rồi xong đến lúc nó mềm ra
it's very shiny and
nó cũng rất là bóng Sờ nó cũng rất là dễ
pleasant to touch, right? But after a while,
chịu phải không Nhưng đến một thời điểm
it starts to rot, and the same goes for a human;
sau nó mới thối và cái con người đấy
it softens, and the body is very
cũng thế nó mềm ra Rồi cơ thể Nó rất
shiny and beautiful, but after some time, the
bóng đẹp nhưng đến thời gian sau bắt đầu
water starts to rise, and that's when it rots.
nước nó ình lên nó mới gì nó mới thối
So, we
nên chúng ta đừng tự lừa dối mình không
shouldn't deceive ourselves; we must have
nên lừa rối mình mà chúng ta phải có cái
practical knowledge and experience. When we
kiến thức thực tế trải nghiệm và khi
hear something, we must think clearly.
nghe cái gì phải tư duy rõ ràng Giàng
We must
điều đó Chúng ta phải biết
understand that chanting Buddha's name in Dharma assemblies or
rõ còn niệm phật ở trong pháp hội hay là
reciting scriptures has its power, but that
tụng kinh nó có công năng của nó nhưng
power is not something that can be otherwise.
không phải cái công năng đó là công năng
Regarding rebirth, the
được vãng sinh mà do cái nghiệp lực của
Buddha taught that the deceased's karma is like this: The
mất đức Phật dạy thế này
deceased is reborn faster
này người chết ấy Nó tái sinh nhanh hơn
than a strongman stretching his fingers or
cả lực sĩ co duỗi ngón co duỗi cái cánh
arm. That is, as soon as a
tay như thế này các quý đạo hữu ạ
person dies,
tức là khi chết một cái thì con người đó
they immediately become another being.
nó đã thành một chúng sinh khác ngay rồi
One is in the heavenly realm, two is human, three is
Một là cõi trời hai là người Ba là súc
animal. That is, they leave the body immediately within these six realms;
sinh Tức là trong lục đạo này nó đi ngay
they don't stay in the body for
rồi chứ không phải nó ở trong cái cơ thể
eight hours or more before
con người này tám tiếng sau hay đến bao
leaving.
nhiêu tiếng nó mới rút ra khỏi cơ
It's the mind. The mind ceases
thể Nó là tâm cơ mà Tâm nó tâm nó dứt ở
here and immediately takes on a physical form elsewhere. It's
đây và nó thành tựu thân ở kia ngay
not like the warmth disappears
Không phải nó là hơi ấm mà bảo là nó hết
from our body.
trong cơ thể của chúng ta cơ thể của
Our body follows the workings of
chúng ta là nó theo cái sự vận hành của
the four elements: earth, water, wind, and sun. For example,
tứ đại đất nước gió nửa thì như cơ thể
our body is at 37 degrees Celsius, and after death,
chúng ta đang 37 độ sau khi chết đến một
it takes some time to cool down.
thời gian nào đó nó mới nguội đi nhưng
But this mind, upon rebirth, immediately
mà cái tâm này nó đi tái sinh thì ngay
ceases breathing and is
lập tức tắt hơi thở một cái nó liền tái
reborn into another being
sinh thành một chúng sinh khác ngay lập
instantly. It's no longer within this physical body.
tức và nó không còn ở trong cái thân tứ
It's simply clinging to the
đại này nữa chẳng qua nó chỉ là chấp cái
body as its own.  For example, if we
thân là của nó thôi ví dụ như là mình
cling to this body as our own, and someone touches it,
chấp cái thân này là của mình ai động
we might get angry or
đến thì mình có thể là mình sân giận hay
something like that. Therefore, we say that
là cái gì đó thôi Thế cho nên mình nói
for someone who has just passed away, we must guide them so they
là người mới mất mình phải khai thị làm
don't cling to the body. That
sao đấy cho người ta đừng chấp thân thế
's our imagination;
thôi Đấy là cái tưởng tượng ra của mình
they are still in the realm of the hungry ghosts,
là họ đang còn trong cõi ngã quỷ còn có
possibly even animals, and many
khả năng họ làm súc sinh và rất là nhiều
other realms. Therefore,
cõi khác rồi Thế cho nên có những cái
these concepts are not
quan niệm đấy là quan niệm chưa được
accurate. We only hear that
chuẩn mà chúng ta chỉ nghe thấy rằ rằng
something is a result of rebirth or
cái được ấy mà được vãng sinh hay là
something like that, and we believe it
được Cái này được cái kia là chúng ta
immediately without verification, and it's wrong. It
tin ngay không có thẩm sát và nó sai có
could be a whole
thể là cả một hệ
system. Why can we affirm the "Returning to the Pure Land" mental perception?
thống tại sao tâm chiếu Hoàn quán có thể
Because the "Returning to the Pure Land" mental perception has
khẳng định bởi vì tâm chiếu Hoàn quán đã
experienced death. Remember,
được chết thử các quý đạo hữu nhớ
before we
này khi chúng ta chưa tắt
completely stop breathing, we and the outside world are
thở hoàn toàn chúng ta và thế giới bên
like you, dear fellow practitioners, sleeping
ngoài giống như các quý đạo hữu đang ngủ
soundly while outside, you don't
say mà bên ngoài hát hò không hề nghe
hear anything. Have you ever been
thấy gì các quý Đạo Hữu đã bao giờ đi
in a car and fallen asleep while reciting Buddha's name? You're
trên xe ô tô mà ngủ cả xe Niệm Phật quý
still dreaming, are
đạo hữu vẫn là mơ
n't you? That's how it is when you die. The "Returning to the
không đấy thì lúc chết nó như thế ạ tâm
Pure Land" mental perception has experienced death, so...
chếu hoàn quán đã chết thử mà cho nên
Our connection with the outside world is
chúng ta với thế giới bên ngoài là vô
meaningless. That's when the mind is still focused on the present moment,
nghĩa Đấy là lúc đấy là tâm chiếu Hoàn
not yet dead. It doesn't receive
quán chưa chết đấy ạ Đã không tiếp nhận
external sounds, and
những âm thanh bên ngoài rồi không tiếp
we chant scriptures and perform rituals,
nhận còn chúng ta tụng kinh lễ bái tất
all with the meaning that
cả các thứ ở đó là với cái ý nghĩa là
the person is already dead. So,
người ta chết rồi cho nên chúng sinh này
if this being is a hungry ghost, then they are
nếu là chúng ngã quỷ thì người ta ở bên
nearby, and we chant scriptures and perform rituals
cạnh đây rồi chúng ta tụng kinh lễ bái
to help that hungry ghost attain enlightenment. It's
để cho ngã quỷ đó giác ngộ chứ không
not that this physical body still has a
phải cái thân tứ đại này nó còn một cái
soul inside, and that soul is there to achieve enlightenment
linh hồn nào ở trong đó nó giác ngộ ở
within it, isn't that right, dear fellow practitioners? And
trong đó không phải các quý đạo hữu ạ Mà
when someone dies, they are immediately
người vừa chết người ta liền lập tức Tái
reborn, faster than the outstretched arm of a practitioner. That person is no longer just a being;
Sinh gọi là nhanh hơn cánh tay LC sĩ có
they are a different being. The moment
Nó là một chúng sinh khác rồi Ngay khi
we stop breathing... So
chúng ta tắt thở
why do some people who are
còn Tại sao lại có những người Chết lâm
clinically dead return?
sàng rồi quay lại các quý đạo hữu Hãy
Remember the sutra where Indra took refuge in the
nhớ lại cái bài kinh mà ông Đế Thích quy
Three Jewels? Indra,
y Tam Bảo
after he was
đi ông trời Đế Thích ý sau khi ông ấy
near death in that heavenly realm, he went to the
gần chết ở cõi trời ấy ông ấy quay đến
Buddha and asked to take refuge in the Three Jewels.
chỗ Đức Phật ông ấy xin quy y Tam Bảo
After that, he died and was immediately reborn
sau khi đó thì ông ấy mạng chung luôn và
into the
ông đọa luôn vào con
first half of his life.  He's finished one lifetime, right? Then,
nửa ông đã đầu thai xong một kiếp rồi
his merit
đấy chứ Thế xong rồi cái Phước của ông
is restored to its original state, and that
lại được hồi lại như cũ và chính cái
merit causes him to return, and
phước đấy làm cho ông ấy quay trở về và
his body comes back to life. That
cái thân của ông ấy sống trở lại thì đó
's the power of karmic retribution; it
là một lăng lực của Phước báo nó tương
corresponds to the physical body that existed before,
ưng với cái thân tứ đại đã có từ trước
so that body comes back to life. It's
cho nên cái thân đó nó sống trở lại chứ
not a soul. That's the
không phải có một linh hồn nào cả Đó là
power of karma. If we
năng lực của nghiệp Nếu chúng ta hình
imagine we have a soul,
dung ra là chúng ta có một cái linh hồn
like us entering
nào đó giống như chúng ta chui Va Ra cửa
and exiting through the door of a house, that's a
nhà và chui vào cửa nhà thì cái đấy là
wrong, mistaken, and deluded view. That's karma, dear fellow
tà kiến sai lầm mê mờ mà đó là nghiệp
practitioners. Let's use
các quý đạo hữu ạ tâm chếu hoàn quán lấy
this example to help you understand:
ví dụ như này cho các quý đạo hữu hiểu
For instance, we have a shirt that costs
ạ ví dụ chúng ta có cái áo này là
50,000. We have 50,000, we
50.000 chúng ta có được 50.000n chúng ta
buy
mua cái áo
this shirt. Then, the karma, as the mind
này Thế thì cái cái mà nghiệp thì tâm
observes, is like that 50,000.
chiếu hòn quán ví cho nó là 50.000 đấy ạ
That's 50,000. That's enough merit to
đấy 50.000 thế là nó đủ Phúc chui đúng
enter that shirt. Do you understand, dear fellow practitioners? Then,
vào cái áo đó quý Đạ Hữu rõ chưa thì ông
God liked it before he left.
trời đấy thích lúc trước ông ấy ra đi
Leaving that physical body means
khỏi cái cái cái cái cái áo Tức là cái
that if he has
thân tứ đại này là ông có cái Phước là
50 parts of merit, he can leave it. However, because
50 thì ông rời khỏi đó thế nhưng mà do
he still has past karma, he is reborn. That is,
ông còn cái nghiệp quá khứ cho nên ông
this physical body must have
bị đọa làm Tức là cái thân tứ đại này là
50 parts of merit to be able to have
đủ 50 phần Phước thì mới có thể có được
that physical body. Then, he
cái thân tứ đại đó Thế sau rồi thì ông
starts to suffer evil, he is reborn as a fire spirit,
ấy bắt đầu ông bị ác ông đọa làm thân
he repays all his karma through his merit of
con nừa ông trả hết nghiệp do cái Phước
taking refuge, and he again has 50 parts of merit.
Quy y của ông ông lại đủ 50 phần Phước
That karma then returns to that
Cái nghiệp đấy nó lại chui về cái thân
physical body. Do you understand, dear fellow practitioners?
tứ đại đấy quý Đạo Hữu có hiểu được
This is because although he
ạ thì cái cái này là ông Tuy rằng ông ấy
has that body, he has already gone through
có cái thân đó như ông đã đi qua đến
three lifetimes. The first lifetime was as a
kiếp thứ ba rồi ạ kiếp thứ nhất là ông
celestial being, in that physical form; the
trời đấy thích trong cái thân tướng như
second lifetime was as a fire spirit; and the
vậy kiếp thứ hai là thân con lửa và kiếp
third lifetime was as a celestial being, still in that physical form,
thứ ba là ông trời đấy thức cũng cái
or with a mind that
thân tướng đó hay tâm chiếu Hoàn quán
reflects the complete contemplation. To give you
nói vị như thế này để cho có quý Đạo Hữu
an example, dear fellow practitioners, two
có một ví dụ để hiểu thêm hai anh em
twins are very similar.
sinh đôi là hai người rất giống nhau đấy
They have relatively similar merit and karma,
là họ có cái Phước nghiệp tương đối
so they have relatively similar physical bodies.
giống nhau cho nên cá Có cái có cái vỏ
Do you understand that, dear fellow practitioners? Therefore,
Hữu có hiểu chỗ đó không Thế cho nên cái
when a person dies at dawn,
con người mà chết Lâm sáng là lúc họ
after they die, they can become some kind of
chết xong rồi họ có thể thành một Chúng
ghost or demon. That's them paying off
ngã quỷ nào rồi Đấy là họ chỉ trả đi cái
their karmic debt at some point in
nghiệp báo của họ lúc nào đó trong thời
time corresponding to their karma, and then they return
gian tương ưng với nghiệp rồi họ lại trở
to their original state of merit. So that physical body
về cái Phước như cũ cho nên thân tứ đại
continues to be theirs; their merit
đó lại tiếp tục là của họ chứ Phước của
doesn't increase. If their merit
họ không tăng lên được Nếu Phước của họ
increased, they could be
tăng lên được thì họ có thể đầu thai làm
reborn as another being with a
người vào một chúng sinh khác có cuộc
different life, but because their merit is limited,
sống khác nhưng do cái Phước nó chỉ thế
they must continue
thôi cho nên nó phải tiếp tục cuộc sống
that life, and their karma is related to their
đó và cái nghiệp thì nó có những cái
family and lineage. They have
nghiệp về gia đình về dòng họ đấy họ có
corresponding karma, and they
cái nghiệp tương ưng như thế và Họ quay
return. So, when we understand Buddhist teachings,
trở lại cho nên chúng ta hiểu Phật pháp
we must understand correctly.
chúng ta phải hiểu đúng
Otherwise, understanding that after eight hours a
Nếu không thì hiểu hiểu là Sau tám tiếng
person leaves
cái người ta mới rút ra khỏi cái thân
this body is called having a soul, and the
này thì đó gọi là có một linh hồn mà đã
theory of a soul is contrary to Buddhism.
thuyết linh hồn là trái với đạo Phật
There is no soul that leaves a
không có một linh hồn nào để rút ra khỏi
person after eight hours, and yet there are
con người Sau tám tiếng hết mà lại còn
places where it comes out, such as the chest, the
có chỗ là đi ra ở nối ngực đi ra ở nối
crown of the head, or the soles of the feet.  In
đỉnh đầu đi ra ở nối bàn chân đi ra ở
Buddhist scriptures, there's
lối đầu gối thực sự trong kinh phật
no such thing as the "knee exit"; that's just something
không có điều đó mà đó là cái cái nói
other practitioners, monks, have said. It's
lại của các vị khác tu hành là các vị sư
not actually in Buddhist scriptures; it's
chứ không có trong kinh phật đó hoàn
entirely written by monks. That's the
toàn là sách viết của các vị sư và đó
theory of the soul:
chính là thuyết linh hồn có một linh hồn
some souls exit through the chest, some
nào đó đi ra lối ngực có linh hồn nào đó
through the head, but not all. And it takes
đi ra lối đầu không có như thế mà sau
eight hours to leave; it's not instantaneous death.
tám tiếng mới đi không phải chết một cái
If someone is reborn, they are reborn
Nếu đã vãng sinh là vãng sinh ngay lập
immediately. No one can assist
tức không Có ai có thể trợ niệm cho
another person in rebirth; rebirth is instantaneous.
người khác vãng sinh mà vãng sinh là
We must understand that knowledge. And what
đó chúng ta phải hiểu được cái kiến thức
if a being,
đó Thế còn nếu như là một chúng sinh đó
after death, becomes a hungry ghost,
sau khi chết bị thành một Chúng ngã quỷ
and this hungry ghost clings to
mà cái chúng ngã quỷ này nó chấp cái
this body as its own? Then we chant scriptures, we perform rituals, we give teachings—we are giving teachings to
thân này là của nó nó chấp thân này của
that hungry ghost,
thị là Khai Thị cho cái chúng ngã quỷ
not to this
cái kìa chứ không phải là Khai Thị cho
person. This person
cái con người này đâu con người này nó
dies and becomes another being, and this being
chết rồi nó thành một chúng sinh khác
clings to the past as
rồi chúng sinh này nó có chấp trước đây
its family. Do you understand this point, Venerable Master?  There is
là gia đình của nó quý Đạ Hữu rõ chỗ này
attachment. They
chưa ạ Đấy là có chấp trước đấy họ vẫn
still consider
họ là kiếp sống khác nhưng họ vẫn Coi
this as their husband, wife, brother,
đây là chồng đây là vợ đây là anh đây là
sister, or child because they have just passed
em đây là con cái vì họ vừa mới mới mới
away. So, where does this attachment to the
mất đấy thì cái mà họ chấp trước vào cái
physical body come from?
xác thân cụ
How can they
là do đâu mà họ lại chấp được sao họ lại
know? Because these hungry ghosts possess
biết được bởi vì chúng ngã quỷ có được
supernatural powers; they know their past. The
thông họ biết được quá khứ của họ đấy
Buddhist scriptures teach this. Therefore, these
kinh Phật đã dạy như vậy rồi cho nên cái
hungry ghosts have supernatural powers to
chúng ngã quỷ Họ có một thần thông ở
some extent. For example, they can know
khoảng nào đó ví dụ họ có thể biết được
about one, two,
là ngay trong một kiếp hoặc hai kiếp
or three past lives. So, when we read the scriptures about hungry ghosts,
hoặc ba kiếp cho nên chúng ta đọc trong
we see that they can
kinh ngã quỷ sự chúng ta có thấy rằng
tell us who their mother was, where she was, and what she did. This is also in the scriptures about hungry ghosts, do
ngã quỷ nó có kể mẹ nó là ai ở đâu làm
you understand? But if there are too many past lives,
quý Đạ Hữu rõ chưa nhưng nhiều kiếp quá
they won't remember, but
thì họ lại không nhớ được nhưng một kiếp
they remember a single past life. In the Buddhist scriptures, they remember a
đó thì họ nhớ được trong kinh phật rất
lot. They all remember because they have
nhiều Chúng đều nhớ được là do chúng có
supernatural powers. All hungry ghosts have this
thông tất cả chúng ngã quỷ nó đều có đặc
characteristic; they have supernatural powers. That's why we see
tính nó có thần thông cho nên chúng ta
fortune-telling ghosts; they know
mới thấy rằng là có quỷ bói đấy nó biết
everything about our house,
được hết nhà mình có cái gì nó kể ra cho
they tell us everything.  Therefore,
mình nó biết hết đấy chứ đấy nhá Cho nên
here we must have knowledge;
ở đây chúng ta phải có kiến thức chúng
we must never be deluded. If we say
ta đừng bao giờ mê lầm Nếu chúng ta nói
that this person has been reborn in the Pure Land, that person has been reborn in the Pure Land,
rằng người này vãng sinh người kia vãng
we don't know anything about it, so we say
sinh chúng ta đâu có biết đâu mà nói như
that. As a result, we are
vậy Thành ra chúng ta
controlled by false views, causing
bị bị cái tà kiến chi phối khiến cho
us to sometimes say things we have
chúng ta đôi khi thành nói những điều
n't seen or known. If we see something we don't know, and then say we know it, and that
không thấy nói Thấy không biết nói biết
someone has been reborn in the
rồi người ta bị đọa ở đâu ấy thì lại bảo
Western Pure Land, then we are
ta được Vãng sinh Tây Phương Thế là mình
saying things that are untrue.
nói những điều sai sự thật thì mình đi
So, if we practice Buddhism in this way, we are creating negative
tu như vậy mình lại trở thành là tạo
karma. The Buddha taught us in
nghiệp Đức phật có dạy chúng ta trong
the lesson on faith: don't be quick to believe what
cái bài lòng tin chớ vội tin điều đó
is said by someone in authority, don't be quick to
được nói ra từ người có uy quyền chớ vội
believe what is said by someone in a position of
tin vì điều đói đó được nói ra từ truyền
authority, don't be quick to believe what is said by someone in a
thống chớ vội tin vì điều đó được nói ra
tradition, don't be quick to believe what is
từ kinh điển chớ vội tin vì điều đó được
said by someone in a scripture, don't be quick to believe what is said by your spiritual teacher. After
nói ra t vị đạo sư của mình mà sau khi
you hear it, you must verify it. Only when you
các ông nghe các ông phải có thẩm sát
verify that it is true should you
sát khi thẩm sát thấy đó là sự thật thì
believe it. What do you, dear fellow practitioners, use to verify the matter of assisting the deceased to be reborn in the Pure Land? Has anyone ever told you about this after death?  It's not that we've been
chết mà lại nói cho mình nghe là mình
reborn into the Pure Land, but people have already passed away.
được vãng sinh đâu người ta đi mất rồi
So we must believe in the
còn đâu nữa cho nên chúng ta phải tin và
law of cause and effect. Therefore, we Buddhists
lý nhân quả cho nên các phật tử chúng
must uphold the precepts. If you don't know, don't say you
ta phải giữ giới không biết đừng nói là
know. If you haven't seen people go to the Western Pure Land,
biết không thấy người ta về tây phương
don't say they've gone to the
thì đừng nói người ta về Tây Phương mà
Western Pure Land. You all want to know what it means to see people go to the Western Pure Land. It's
người ta về Tây Phương là thế nào
not like this: Now, you
Không thế này ạ Các Quý đạo hữu bây giờ
just go out on the street, stand at a crossroads, and you
chỉ đi ra ngoài đường thôi đứng ở ngã ba
see someone going to the left towards Dong Anh, then to the
thấy người ta đi bên trái đến Đông Anh
right towards Lam Tu Liem. Of course, you
đi đến phải lam Tử Liêm đương nhiên các
must know the road
quý đạo hữu phải biết được cái con đường
to Lam Tu Liem, the road
đi đến Lam tử Niêm con đường đi
to Dong Anh. You must
đến đi đến Đông Anh phải biết mình phải
know it to see them going,
biết thì mình mới thấy người ta đi được
right? You haven't even seen
chứ phải không Mình còn chưa thấy người
how they went, and you're already saying you
ta đi bằng cách nào mà mình đã bảo mình
saw them go to the Western Pure Land. You don't know
thấy họ về Tây Phương Mình có biết thấy
how they went. Let me
đi bằng cách nào đâu tâm chếu Hàn quán
tell you, dear fellow practitioners, there's a
kể cho các quý đạo hữu nghe có một chị
woman in the Pure Land practice of reciting Buddha's name. She
chị ý ở trong Pháp môn niệm Phật Chị ý
said this:
bảo thế này chứ
In the Three-Time Recitation Assembly,
ở trong cái pháp Hội Tam Thời Hệ Niệm ấy
when Amitabha Buddha shines his light
khi mà Phật a di đà mà mà chiếu Hảo
down on the departed soul...  Chasing after the
Quang xuống vong linh nó chạy theo cái
halo to go to the Western Paradise, some
hào quang để đi về Tây Phương có những
spirits can't even stop in time. Oh no, they're
vong linh chạy không kịp đứng lại Ô thôi
dead! People are reborn in heaven
chết rồi người ta sinh lên cõi trời còn
faster than a strongman stretching and bending their
nhanh hơn cả lực sĩ co duỗi
arms, and yet they're reborn in another realm so
tay cơ mà người ta sinh về cõi lào nó
quickly! And
nhanh đến mức độ như thế cơ mà mà lại
here, there's this image of
đây còn có cái hình dạng là chạy theo
spirits chasing after each other to be reborn in the
vong linh chạy theo để vãng sinh Tây
Western Paradise under the light of Amitabha Buddha. It's
Phương theo ánh sáng của đức Phật A di
truly unbelievable!
đà quả thật là tưởng tượng ra Khéo quá
How can people be reborn?
sao có thế người ta tái sinh cơ mà thế
But how can we see
thì làm sao mà mình nhìn thấy cái sự tái
their rebirth?
sinh của người ta
They're so fast, and
được người ta nhanh đến mức độ như thế
yet we say we can see
này mà lại bảo là nhìn thấy được người
them reborn, and even see them
ta tái sinh lại còn nhìn thấy người ta
running!
chạy nữa chứ mà nó từ cái thân con này
They go from one body to another. It's a
nó đi thân con khác Nó là một hình dáng
different form, and to reach Amitabha Buddha's realm, they
khác mà muốn về đến cõi Phật A Di Đà là
change their form. They're no longer
nó thay đổi hình tướng rồi chứ không
ghosts, nor are they
phải là ngã quỷ nữa cũng không phải là
humans anymore. They change their
con người nữa mà người ta thay đổi hình
form, they're reborn, they're reborn themselves. It's
tướng người ta sinh người ta tự sinh ra
not like they
đấy thôi chứ không phải là lại còn phải
need time to walk from here to Amitabha Buddha's realm
có thời gian đi bộ từ đây đến cõi Phật A
or run to Amitabha Buddha's realm.
Di Đà hay là phải chạy đến cõi Phật A di
That's a lot of imagination, a lot of
đà thật sự đó là cái sự tưởng tượng
contemplation, so when
tưởng tượng rất là nhiều đấy cho nên khi
we hear something from
chúng ta nghe chúng ta nghe một vị nào
someone, we shouldn't believe it. If we
đó chúng ta đừng tin nếu cái điều đó
can't verify it, we shouldn't believe it,
Chúng ta không thẩm sát được thì đừng
right? We haven't verified it yet, so how can we
tin đúng không đã thẩm sát được đâu mà
believe it? The concept of "hardness and softness" in the mind's contemplation is like a
tin nhá thì cái việc cứng mềm tâm chiếu
fish, to make it
Hoàn quán lý con cá ra để cho các quý
easier for you to understand. A fish is
đạo hữu dễ hình dung phải không con cá
alive, then it stops breathing, it dies, and it becomes soft.
nó đang sống nó tắt Hơi Thở nó chết một
After a while, it becomes hard again.
cứng rồi Để một thời điểm nào đó nó lại
Humans are the same; when a person
mềm con người cũng thế
dies, they only remain soft for a
chết một cái thì nó chỉ mềm cho một thời
while. Remember this, dear fellow practitioners. Remember
gian sau đó đây nhớ các quý đạo hữu Nhớ
this to cultivate contemplation. Let me add
thế này để tâm chếu hoàn quán nói thêm
another characteristic for you to
một cái đặc điểm nữa để cho các quý đạo
consider: Firstly, the muscles contract, so when a
hữu theo dõi này Thứ nhất là cơ nó co
person dies, their
cho nên con người ta chết một cái thì
eyes open and their mouth gapes open. That's because the muscles pull,
mắt bị mở mồm bị há Đấy là do cơ nó kéo
they hurt, and they pull. When a person dies, their eyes open and their mouth gapes open,
nó đau nó kéo thi chết một cái là mắt mở
but if left like that for a
ra mồm há ra nhưng cứ để như vậy đến một
while, the muscles soften, the eyes close on their own, and the mouth closes on its own.
thời gian nào đó cơ nó mềm ra mắt nó tự
Why do our people believe that
Tại sao dân của chúng ta lại tin theo
chanting Buddha's name makes the body soft? It's because...
cái điều là là niệm phật nó mềm là do từ
Until now, when a family member died,
trước tới nay khi gia đình có người chết
they quickly wrapped the body up, fearing
một cái thì họ nhanh nhẹn bó vào họ sợ
it would harden, so they didn't
để đến đâu nó cứng cho nên họ đâu có
witness the process of it hardening and
chứng kiến cái cảnh nó cứng vào và nó
softening. Then, now, with the Funeral Assistance Team, they don't
mềm ra đâu Xong đến bây giờ có đội Trợ
allow wrapping or doing
Niệm đến không cho bó vào không cho làm
anything else, and we can observe the process from soft to
gì và chúng ta theo dõi được từ mềm đến
hard to soft again. So, when they say it's rebirth, we believe it's
cứng đến mềm cho nên bảo đó là vãng sinh
true. Do you understand, dear friends? The
mình cứ tưởng thật các quý đầu Hữu rõ
Lord's mind, the Complete Enlightenment, has also allowed this
ạ tâm Chúa Hoàn quán cũng đã để cho cái
benefit; it's the mother of the mind's reflection. Complete Enlightenment is gone, only the
hời đấy là u là mẹ cả của tâm chiếu Hoàn
mind's reflection remains at
quán mất mỗi mình tâm chiếu Hoàn quán ở
home; there's no chanting of Buddha's name or anything. What is he doing here?  There
nhà chứ có niệm phật gì đâu Làm gì ở đấy
were no Buddhists around, just one person. Then,
làm gì có phật tử đâu một mình
when the monks arrived to chant, the
mà Thì tới khi mà các thầy về niệm thì
congregation had only just arrived a little while ago.
đạo tràng cũng mới về đến nơi một chút
After the monks finished chanting, they lifted the body from the
thôi thì các thầy về niệm rồi thì bế từ
bed; it was so soft. The mind of the deceased, Hoan Quan,
trong giường ra nó mềm thế mà tâm ch
didn't chant a single Buddhist mantra,
Hoàn quán không niệm phật một câu
only giving guidance to the mother before she passed away.
nào chỉ Khai Thị cho mẹ trước lúc mất
Not a single word at all. Because the mind
thôi không hề một câu lào hết vì tâm
of Hoan Quan had a little bit of spirituality,
chiếu Hoàn quán có một chút tâm linh cho
when they lifted her out and placed her in the coffin, she was so soft. No
nên đến lúc bế ra đi đi nhập quan mềm
one chanted a single Buddhist mantra, not a single Buddhist. The mind of the deceased, Hoan Quan,
quý đạo hữu ạ không có một người nào
chanted a single sutra, not a single one. The
tụng không tục một bài kinh
mind of the deceased, Hoan Quan, was alone
nào một mình tâm chếu hoàn
before she passed away, cultivating Bodhicitta (the aspiration for enlightenment).
quán trước khi u mất cho Phát Tâm Bồ Đề
Then she collapsed and passed away. The
xong xong cái là u gục xuống mất luôn và
mind of the deceased immediately
tâm chiếu Hoàn Quán bạch luôn xong cái
understood, and then they placed the body
biết được rồi cái cho thân xác nằm vào
in the bed, lifting her in. It was
trong giường luôn bế vào trong giường cứ
soft and then stiff, until it became soft again. When
thế rồi cứ mềm cứ cứng rồi đến lúc mềm
the monks arrived and placed her in the coffin, she was completely limp. No
các thầy về nhập quan mềm nhũn Chả thấy
one chanted a single Buddhist mantra, dear fellow practitioners.
ai niệm câu nào đấy các quý đạo hữu ạ
We must contemplate the
Chúng ta phải chiêm nghiệm sự
truth, we must verify it, because
thật chúng ta phải chứng nghiệm vì cái
this is very easy. If you, dear fellow practitioners, wish,
điều này rất dễ nếu các quý đạo hữu muốn
if a family member
thì nếu người nhà của các quý đạo hữu
passes away, you can...  The body is still there, just
mất các quý đạo hữu cứ đầ yên đấy chỉ
offering prayers to the Buddha. We
bạch Phật cúng dường thôi chúng ta có
can enlighten the departed soul, but if
thể khai thị cho vong linh nhưng chúng
we don't do anything, it will eventually soften, the
ta không làm gì rồi nó cũng sẽ mềm rồi
skin will become soft, the eyes will become taut, the mouth will
là da rẻ nó cũng sẽ căng mắt nó cũng sẽ
close, and the lips will be shut.
nhắm mồm nó cũng sẽ ngậm các quý đạo hữu
These are physical phenomena.
đấy là hiện tượng vật
Just look at the corpses in the morgue;
lý đấy cứ xem những xác chết ở trên nhà
ask the doctors who monitor them. It's the
xác hỏi bác sĩ người ta theo dõi mà xem
same; there's no difference. So
Nó cũng thế mà nó khác gì đâu cho nên ở
here, we must have knowledge, but
đây chúng ta phải có kiến thức nhưng
we can't explain everything to everyone
chúng ta không thể nói hết với mọi người
so they understand.
để người ta hiểu điều này được thì chúng
As disciples of the Buddha, having learned the
ta là người đệ tử Phật được học chính
Buddha's true Dharma, we must understand this so there's
pháp của Phật chúng ta phải hiểu để
no confusion. The time it takes for the
không có hoang mang gì hết cái thời gian
body to change from stiff
của người chết có thân từ cứng chuyển
to soft after death—what is that time? It's sufficient. That time, the time it takes for the body to gradually stiffen and soften—
sang mềm thời gian của nó là gì nó là đủ
that time is sufficient, depending on
cái thời gian đó là đủ độ thời gian của
each person's physical constitution, the four elements of the body, and whether there was
cơ địa của mỗi người của cái thân tứ đại
more or less stiffness before death. That is, when
cứng nhiều hay co cứng ít Tức là cái
death occurs, the
chết diễn ra người ta bị những cái vận
body experiences movements that conflict with pain—the pain of
động trong cơ nó đối chọi với cái Đau
letting go of this body,
cái đau của cái sự xả bỏ cái thân này
the pain of...  Death is the suffering of death, the
cái đau của sự chết đấy khổ của chết mà
suffering of birth, old age, sickness, and death. The suffering of
khổ của sinh già bệnh chết thì cái khổ
death is like a turtle retracting its shell, so
chết là khổ như rùa rút mai sống cho nên
that pain causes the body to
cái đau đó khiến cho người đó có cái sự
move its muscles,
vận động của các
but it's not visible from the outside.
mà không có được cái nhìn thấy ở bên
That's the movement of the body's muscles. When the body stiffens,
ngoài đó là vận động của cái Lỗi cơ thể
the pain is worse, and
này co cứng thì cái đau Lào nhiều thì
the time it takes for the muscles to relax is longer.
cái thời gian nó mềm cơ nó lâu hơn còn
Those who experience less pain
người nào đau ít thì cái thời gian mềm
will have a shorter time for muscle
Cơ nó sẽ ít
relaxation, and their minds will be focused. The same goes for the
tâm chiếu Hoàn quán cũng chia sẻ thế này
two Zen masters at Dau Pagoda.
hai vị thiền sư ở trên chùa Đậu ấy các
They sit in the lotus position, and
vị ấy ngồi kiết già đấy ngồi kiết già mà
after sacrificing their bodies, they become two
xả thân xong rồi trở thành hai nhục thân
physical relics. So, if they were stiff, then according to the
xá lợi đấy Thế các vị có cứng Thế thì
theory of assisted recitation, they would surely have fallen into damnation. They were
thuyết trợ niệm này chắc đọa rồi À cứng
very stiff, still sitting in the lotus position, and they didn't relax at all.
lắm ngồi vẫn kiết ra mà nó có mềm ra đâu
So,
Thế
how would you explain that, my
thì các quý đạo hữu giải thích thế nào
fellow practitioners? Therefore,
không đấy nhá Quý đạo hữu nhá cho nên
we must have very
chúng ta phải phải có cái kiến thức thật
thorough knowledge of this point. These two Zen masters
kỹ chỗ này các vị thiền sư hai vị thiền
are enlightened practitioners, so they
sư là hai vị tu đắc đạo cho nên hai vị
intended to leave their physical bodies behind to...
có ý muốn để cái nhục thân đó để mà mà
Because others have faith,
khiến cho người khác có lòng tin cho nên
these two enlightened Zen masters
hai vị thiền sư đắc đạo này mới có cái
manifested themselves, their physical bodies taking on the
cái thị hiện ra để cho cái thân tứ đại
form of
của các vị ý là nó sẽ có cái hình dáng
meditating, to help others increase their
ngồi thiền để cho người khác tăng trưởng
faith in the Buddha Dharma and their
cái tín tâm đối với lại Phật Pháp với
attainment of enlightenment. Therefore, they made a vow. Dear fellow
cái sự chứng Đắc thế cho nên các vị có
practitioners, do you understand this point? It's
nguyện C Quý đội Hữu rõ chỗ này chưa ạ
similar to a
Giống như chúng ta trong một cái trường
case we've learned about: if an
hợp mà chúng ta đã được học đấy nếu vị A
Arhat makes a vow, upon death, the Golden
la hán nào mà họ có nguyện thì khi chết
Light Coffin might fly up, rise, and
có thể là Kim Quang Quan bay lên nâng
fall three times. It might manifest in other ways. This
lên hạ xuống ba lần đấy có thể là có
is due to the
những cái này có cái kia Đấy là do
vows of these enlightened beings.
nguyện của các vị chứng Đắc này thì
Whatever vows they made before death,
trước khi chết các vị có nguyện thế nào
they will experience them afterward. So,
thì sau thì các vị sẽ có cái điều đó
dear fellow practitioners,
nhá Thế thì ở đây các quý đạo hữu chúng
we must clearly understand this so that
ta phải rõ rõ biết về việc này để chúng
we never create
ta không bao giờ bị tạo ra những cái
mistakes, such as being
những cái điều sai lầm đó là chúng ta có
confused or violating precepts.
thể mơ hồ và chúng ta có thể bị phạm
Each time we assist in chanting, we speak falsely and carelessly, which is not
giới Mỗi một lần đi trợ niệm lại là
good for us because
ngữ thì không tốt cho chúng ta bởi vì ai
everyone is subject to the law of karma.
ai cũng bị sự chi phối của nhân quả cả
Anyone who does anything outside the cycle of cause and effect, you know.
thôi không ai làm ra ngoài vòng nhân quả
So, esteemed fellow
hết ấy nha Thì Kính thưa các quý đạo
practitioners, regarding the matter of those who pass
hữu Còn về việc của người vãng sinh
away, the one assisting with the funeral rites who claims
ý mà cái người trợ liệm mà bảo rằng là
they have been reborn in the Pure Land—to achieve
họ được vãng sinh ấ thì muốn vãng sinh
that, they must possess sufficient Faith, Practice, and
được ấy thì phải đủ yếu tố Tín Hạnh
Vow. This person, while alive,
Nguyện có thể Cái người này lúc sống chả
knew nothing of Buddhism, right? They didn't know
biết gì Phật cả đúng không Chả biết tây
who the Western Pure Land was, and had no virtuous conduct whatsoever.
phương là ai mà chả có cái Hạnh gì cả
After assisting with chanting for hours,
đến trợ niệm bao nhiêu tiếng đồng hồ
seeing the person soften, they are said to have been reborn in the
thấy người mềm ra bảo vãng sinh Tây
Western Pure Land. Where is the faith, practice, and vow? Just a
Phương Thế tín hạnh nguyện ở đâu Có mỗi
few hours of assistance, and they can enlighten
mấy tiếng trợ lệm mà giác ngộ được cho
a being, make that being
một chúng sinh mà làm cho chúng sinh đấy
completely pure, achieve faith, practice, and vows, purify their three karmas,
thanh tịnh hẳn hoi thành tựu được tín
purify them to be like a
được hạnh được nguyện mà cho họ thanh
Buddha, and achieve purity in the Western Pure Land—
tịnh được ba nghiệp thanh tịnh đồng Phật
that's a whole different matter. When you, esteemed fellow
được nó là cả một vấn đề khi các quý đạo
practitioners, give guidance to the departed soul, when the soul is
hữu Khai Thị cho vong linh vong linh bị
possessed, you
nhập vấy các quý đạo
read countless verses, but if you haven't accumulated enough merit, will the soul accept the path? Then,
hữu đọc bao nhiêu câu mà chưa có phước
this is simply a matter of a departed
không Thế thì đây cũng chẳng qua chỉ là
soul, and you just sit there chanting Buddha's name and
vong linh thôi mà cứ ngồi Niệm Phật xong
tell them they've been reborn in the Western Pure Land,
tí bảo họ những Vãng Tây phương cơ chứ
not to mention alleviating their suffering.  We're going
chưa nói là là bớt khổ và chúng ta lại
back to the Buddhist scriptures again, the
chở lại bộ kinh của Phật nữa đó là kinh
Sutra of the Hungry Ghosts Beyond the Wall, and many,
ngã quỷ ngoại bức tường rồi nhiều nhiều
many more sutras. Those sutras about the hungry ghosts even include the
lắm nhiều bài kinh lắm các kinh ngã quỷ
Buddha himself.
đấy gặp cả Phật rồi đấy ạ Phật phu sa
The Buddha himself told them
rồi đấy mà Đức Phật phu Sa còn bảo chúng
that during the time of Shakyamuni Buddha,
ngã quỷ là đến thời Đức Phật Thích Ca có
his relative, King Bimbisara, would
người thân của ông là vua Bình Sa sẽ
offer alms to
cúng dường lên Đức
Shakyamuni Buddha and the Sangha, dedicating the
Phật Thích Ca và tăng chúng hồi hướng
merit to them so they could be freed from suffering. So, the
phước cho các ông các ông được thoát khổ
Buddha himself and his Sangha are
hóa ra là Phật phu Sa và tăng đoàn của
not as capable as those who
sa không có năng lực bằng mấy người đi
chant Buddha's name and assist in chanting? Isn't that
niệm Phật trợ niệm hay
too arrogant,
sao như thế có quá Là ngã mạn không các
dear fellow practitioners? Even
quý đạo hữu phải
the Buddha couldn't do it, and
không Đức Phật còn không thể làm được mà
they came to see the Buddha, and
họ đến diện Kiến Đức Phật rồi đấy ạ mà
still couldn't. We read many
cũng không được cơ mà chúng ta đọc nhiều
sutras. One day, Sariputta passed
bài kinh lắm một hôm Ngài Xá Lợi Phất đi
by a place where a hungry ghost was lying there,
qua chỗ này có một con quỷ nằm ở cũng
sadly asking Sariputta about this and
buồn hỏi Ngài Xá Lợi Phất về chuyện nọ
that, "Why am I suffering so much?" Does that mean Sariputta
chuyện kia làm sao tôi khổ thế này thế
lacks the ability to help those hungry ghosts be reborn in the
có năng lực chứ cho cái chúng ngã quỷ
Western Pure Land? Does that mean he's
đấy nó vãng sinh Tây phương được à Không
not as capable as us? Isn't that right,
năng lực lại không bằng chúng ta hay sao
dear fellow practitioners?  Therefore,
phải không quý đạo hữu đấy cho nên chúng
we must think deeply. Otherwise,
ta phải tư duy thật sâu sắc Nếu không
we might commit the sin
thì chúng ta có khi lại phạm vào cái tội
of disrespecting the saints, becoming
là coi thường các cái bậc thánh rồi
too arrogant and delusional about our own power, falling
chúng ta quá cái ngã mạn
into the trap of karma, the illusion of power, thinking
mắc vào cái nghiệp là ảo tưởng sức mạnh
we can chant Buddha's name to help
là chúng ta có thể niệm phật để cho ai
someone be reborn in the Pure Land.
đó được vãng sinh nho riêng câu lạc bộ
But the Golden Chrysanthemum Club doesn't do
cúc vàng thì chúng ta không làm cái điều
that. We
đó nh không làm cái điều đó mà chúng ta
must truly see and know before we can
phải thật thấy thật biết thì chúng ta
do that. We must truly
mới mới làm điều đó Chúng ta thật sự
know; if we don't know, we can't. The
biết còn chúng ta chưa biết thì không
Buddhist scriptures are incredibly vast.
thể trong kinh của Phật thì nhiều vô
There's one thing we must
cùng Có một điều mà chúng ta phải đặt
question: the Buddhist scriptures talk so much about
hỏi trong kinh của Phật nói quá nhiều về
these things, yet
những cái việc này thế nhưng mà có những
some people in
cái người nào đó ở trong cái Pháp môn
this blind chanting practice make a requirement for
trợn niệm này đưa ra một cái yêu cầu cho
their disciples: they must not be
người đệ tử của mình là không được Phan
distracted, they must only single-mindedly chant Amitabha Buddha's name and
Duyên chỉ Nhất Tâm Niệm Phật A Di Đà và
not read other scriptures.
không được đọc bộ kinh khác chính cái
Because of this requirement, they don't know what the Buddha said, they
cho nên không biết được Phật nói gì
don't know about the realm of the hungry ghosts that the
không biết được cái cảnh sống ngã quỷ mà
Buddha described. They block
Phật nói ra sao Bịt hết con đường tìm
everyone's path to understanding and simply believe.  That's right,
hiểu của mọi người và y cứ tin đúng như
just one recitation of Buddha's name is enough. The Amitabha Sutra, the Sutra of
vậy thôi một câu niệm phật đó thôi và bộ
Infinite Life, and the Sutra of
kinh a di đà Bộ Kinh Vô Lượng Thọ và Bộ
Contemplation of Infinite Life don't
Kinh Quán Vô Lượng Thọ thì lại chưa hề
mention anything about the realm of hungry ghosts. The
nói gì đến việc cảnh sống của cõi ngã
Sutra of Contemplation of Infinite Life teaches 16 contemplation
quỷ Bộ Kinh Quán Vô Lượng Thọ thì dạy 16
practices and the Three Blessings for rebirth in the Pure Land. If someone
pháp quán và Tam Phước vãng sinh nếu ai
practices all 16 contemplation
mà thực hành được đủ 16 pháp quán đấy
practices and achieves them, they will be
thành tựu 16 pháp quán đấy thì được vãng
reborn in the Western Pure Land. Secondly, achieving the Three
sinh Tây Phương thứ hai là thành tựu Tam
Blessings for rebirth in the
Phước vãng sinh thì được vãng sinh Tây
Western Pure Land is also possible. Chapter 25 of the Sutra of Infinite Life
phương và kinh Kinh Vô Lượng Thọ trong
also states that to be reborn in the Western Pure Land, one
phẩm thứ 25 cũng nói về muốn vãng sinh
must have the Three Blessings for rebirth. The
tây phương thì phải có Tam Phước vãng
merits of the Three
sinh đầy đủ công đức của Tam Phước vãng
Blessings are: firstly, filial piety towards parents, serving
sinh thứ nhất là Hiếu dưỡng cha mẹ phụng
teachers, compassion, non-killing, and cultivating the Ten Good
sự Sư trưởng từ tâm mất sát tu 10 Thiện
Deeds; secondly, strict adherence to precepts; and
Nghiệp thứ hai là nghiêm Trì dưới cấm
thirdly, deep faith in karma, developing Bodhicitta, and
thứ ba là tin sâu nhân quả Phát Tâm Bồ
cultivating merits for rebirth. Only with all these Three Blessings can one be
Đề tu các công đức hồi hướng vãng sinh
reborn in the Pure Land. But even if we cultivate for a
sinh mà bằng con người chúng ta tu cả
lifetime, we may not necessarily achieve it, right? Filial piety towards
đời chưa chắc đã được đúng không phụng
parents, serving teachers, compassion, non-killing, cultivating good deeds, strict adherence to precepts,
dưỡng cha Mẹ Là phụng sự Sư trưởng này
deep faith in karma, and developing
Nghiêm Trì giấy cấm tin sâu nhân quả
Bodhicitta are all necessary.  The Bodhi mind cultivates merits to attain
Phát Tâm Bồ Đề tu các công đức mới được
rebirth in the Pure Land, yet here, a person only
vãng sinh thế mà đây một con người chỉ
has an army of people assisting in their recitation of the Buddha's name to achieve rebirth. Oh, then what's the point of cultivating? It's just
có một đội quân đến trợ niệm cho tí vãng
tiring, is
sinh Ôi thế thì Tu làm gì cho nó mệt ra
n't it? The Sutra of Infinite Life is a
phải không Bộ Kinh Vô Lượng Thọ là tổng
compilation of the Sutras that encompass the meanings
hợp của Bộ Kinh nói hết các cái ý nghĩa
of the Sutra of Contemplation of Infinite Life and the
của cái Bộ Kinh Quán Vô Lượng Thọ và
Amitabha Sutra. To
kinh a di đà kinh a di đà ấy mà muốn trì
recite the Buddha's name, one must practice for seven days or
niệm hồng danh Phật ấy là bảy ngày hoặc
one day, that is, 24 hours a day, diligently
là một ngày một ngày tức là 24 tiếng
reciting the Buddha's name without eating,
chúng ta công thư phu thử không ăn không
drinking, or doing anything else,
uống không làm gì cứ thế niệm phật mà nó
without distraction. It's not about reciting with your mouth while your
lại không loạn cơ chứ không phải mồm
mind wanders; that's
niệm mà đầu lại còn vọng tưởng cái đấy
not enough merit for rebirth.
chưa đủ công đức vãng sinh mà phải trước
Before death, one must have one
khi chết ấy chúng ta phải có từ 1 cho
to seven days of single-mindedness without
tới 7 ngày Nhất Tâm Bất
distraction. This is what is
Loạn đấy là một cái
called a sign of rebirth in the
mà gọi là ấn chứng cho cái người cái
Western Pure Land, allowing one to
người muốn vãng sinh Tây phương để tự
see for oneself whether one is destined for rebirth in the
mình xem mình có là người vãng sinh Tây
Western Pure Land. That is, before
Phương hay không Tức là tự mình trước
death, if one sees that for 24 hours
khi chết mình thấy mình 24 tiếng đồng hồ
one has recited the Buddha's name without distraction,
mình niệm phật mà tâm mình không loạn
then one can affirm that one is destined for
thì mình tự khẳng định là mình được vãng
rebirth in the Western Pure Land. Or, for seven days one can
sinh Tây Phương hoặc là bảy ngày tự mình
recite the Buddha's name.  If I feel that I am not distracted, then I
niệm mình thấy mình không loạn thì mình
know I will be reborn in the Western Pure Land. But
biết là mình vãng sinh Tây Phương Nhưng
if I am still distracted, I will not be
nếu như còn loạn thì không được vãng
reborn in the Western Pure Land. Therefore, the Amitabha Sutra
sinh Tây Phương cho nên Bộ Kinh A Di Đà
clearly explains to me
là bộ kinh nói rõ cho mình chỉ cho mình
the realm of Amitabha Buddha and what kind of
cái cảnh giới của đức Phật A Di Đà và
person is reborn
người như thế nào được vãng sinh thây
there. It is for my own
phương đó là nói cho tự một mình mình
understanding only. Whether I am distracted while reciting the Buddha's name
biết chứ Còn khi mình niệm phật ấy mình
or not, others do
có loạn hay không người ngoài có biết
n't know. Therefore, don't think
hữu không biết được cho nên đừng nghĩ là
you can know if others are reborn. The
mình có thể biết người khác vãng sinh mà
Amitabha Sutra tells you whether
bộ kinh a di đà nói để cho mình biết
you are reborn or not; it's up to you,
mình có vãng sinh hay không là chính
not for
mình thôi chứ không phải để cho người
others to know.
khác biết mình có vãng sinh hay không có
If we recite the Buddha's name for 24 hours a day with a single-minded,
ạ nhá tự chúng ta niệm phật một ngày
undisturbed concentration—that is, 24 hours in total—with our mouths,
Nhất Tâm Bất Loạn tức là 24 tiếng đấy
ears, and heads focused without any distracting
mồm đọc tai nghe đầu hướng theo không hề
thoughts, then we will know we have
một vọng tưởng nào thì mình biết mình sẽ
enough merit to be
đủ công đức vãng
reborn. We also cultivate the Three
sinh còn tự chúng ta chúng ta tu Tam
Blessings for rebirth in the Western Pure Land.
Phước vãng sinh chúng ta hồi hướng tây
When we have enough merit, we leave the physical body and go
phương lúc Lào đủ phước thì bỏ báo thân
to the Western Pure Land. The mind is in the state of complete contemplation. I
là tự về Tây Phương Tâm chố Hoàn quán
repeat, this is the Sutra of Contemplation of Infinite Life.
nhắc lại này Bộ Kinh Quán Vô Lượng Thọ
The Sutra of Infinite Life and the Amitabha Sutra
Bộ Kinh Vô Lượng Thọ và bộ kinh a di đà
both describe
thì trong ba bộ kinh này đều nói lên
the realm of Amitabha Buddha. The Sutra of Contemplation of
cảnh giới của Đức Đức Phật A Di Đà cảnh
Infinite Life describes the practices
Vô Lượng Thọ thì nói lên là các pháp tu
that enable us to be reborn in the Western Pure Land. This is the
để cho chúng ta có thể vãng sinh Tây
practice of contemplation, which is called
Pháp quán đó thuộc gọi là thiền tu thiền
meditation. The practice of 16 complete contemplations,
tu 16 pháp quán đầy đủ 16 pháp quán quán
when followed as instructed, leads to rebirth in the Western Pure
được như hướng dẫn thì được vãng sinh
Land. Secondly, in the Sutra of Contemplation of
Tây Phương thứ hai ở trong Bộ Kinh Quán
Infinite Life, there are the Three Blessings of Rebirth.
Vô Lượng Thọ là Tam Phước vãng sinh
We fully practice these when our minds are
chúng ta thực hành đầy đủ khi tâm chúng
completely free from any unfilial thoughts,
ta hoàn toàn không còn một Khởi niệm bất
when we serve our teachers
hiếu khi chúng ta đã phụng sự Sư trưởng
with reverence, without a single
với cái tâm tôn kính không còn một mảy
disrespectful thought. Thirdly, there is the compassionate non-killing,
niệm nào bất kính thứ ba là từ tâm bất
when our minds are completely free from any
sát khi chúng ta tâm của chúng ta không
thoughts of killing
còn một mảy vọng niệm nào sát hại chúng
living beings. We ourselves
sinh và tự thân chúng ta chúng ta tự
must observe whether we have strictly observed the
phải quán sát xem chúng ta đã nghiêm Trì
precepts. As Buddhists, we may
giới cấm chưa chứ còn phật tử chúng ta
not yet know whether we have violated any precepts, whether false speech or lies.
vọng ngữ và nói dối còn chưa biết phải
We must know that we have
không tự chúng ta phải biết chúng ta
not violated any precepts, whether precepts
không hề phạm vào một giới cấm nào giới
or auxiliary precepts.  A pure and
và tá giới không hề phạm với khu thanh
tranquil place, and also a deep belief in
tịnh và nữa là tin sâu nhân quả tin sâu
karma. A person with a deep belief in karma would never
nhân quả thì cái người này không bao giờ
dare to speak of things they don't know, right? They wouldn't
dám nói ra những điều mình không biết
speak of things they don't understand, would they? They would speak of having a
phải không khôngết rõ mà lại nói ra tin
deep belief in karma, developing Bodhicitta, and possessing immense merit. This
sâu nhân quả Phát Tâm Bồ Đề và người này
merit is fully accumulated through reciting scriptures
đức ở trên ấy đầ đủ đọc tụng kinh điển
and dedicating merit to rebirth in the Pure Land. This includes the Sutra of Contemplation of
và Hồi Hướng vãng sinh đấy là Kinh Quán
Infinite Life and the Amitabha Sutra, which also
Vô Lượng Th nh còn kinh a di đà thì cũng
speaks of the realm of Amitabha Buddha and
nói về cảnh giới của đức Phật A di đà và
states that to be reborn in the Pure Land of Amitabha Buddha, one must possess
nói là muốn sinh về được cõi Phật A di
not only good roots, merit, and
đà thì không phải là ít thiện căn phước
karmic connections, but also the ability to recite the
đức nhân duyên đâu mà phải trì danh niệm
Buddha's name until one reaches single-mindedness without distraction. That is,
Phật cho đến Nhất Tâm Bất Loạn tức là
when we recite the Buddha's name, we have no distracting
khi chúng ta Niệm Phật chúng ta không có
thoughts. The time spent reciting the
một vọng tưởng nào mà cái thời gian niệm
Buddha's name is crucial for proving our ability to be
phật để ấn chứng rằng chúng ta có thể
reborn in the Western Pure Land. We must
vãng sinh Tây phương đó là chúng ta phải
first examine this: we can recite for
kiểm tra bài trước chúng ta có thể niệm
24 hours a day, or
một ngày 24 tiếng hoặc 7 ngày mỗi ngày
24 hours a day for seven days, without any distracting thoughts. Only then will
24 tiếng mà không một vọng niệm nào thì
we have enough merit for rebirth. The sutra
chúng ta mới đủ công đức vãng sinh đế bộ
teaches this in great detail so that we
kinh dạy rất chi tiết để cho chúng ta
don't fall into deluded speech or become
không bị mắc vào vọng ngữ không bị điên
confused. Dear fellow practitioners, we ourselves...  We can
đảo Câ quý đạo hữu ạ tự chúng ta tự ấn
certify that we have sufficient merit for
chứng cho chúng ta là tôi đầy đủ công
rebirth in the Pure Land when we recite the Buddha's name for
đức vãng sinh khi bản thân mình niệm một
24 hours straight without any distracting thoughts.
nào đấy 24 tiếng đồng hồ không còn một
We practice by eating,
vọng niệm nào Tu rằng ăn cơm thì có ăn
but our minds must still be reciting the
cơm nhưng trong đầu vẫn phải đang niệm
Buddha's name. Even when going to the bathroom or going anywhere, we must still be reciting the
phật Tuy rằng đi vệ sinh đi đâu thì
Buddha's name, but we must not
trong đầu vẫn niệm phật nhưng không
sleep.
ngủ
If we do sleep, our minds must
đấy nếu mà có ngủ thì có lẽ trong đầu
still be reciting the Buddha's name. If we are clear about this, then
cũng là niệm phật phải rõ biết thì chắc
we certainly won't sleep. We must pass
chắn là không ngủ rồi chúng ta phải trả
this test; it's a test. We must stay awake for
bài bài đấy là bài kiểm tra chúng ta
24 hours straight, reciting the Buddha's name without
thức 24 tiếng đồng hồ mà niệm không một
sleeping
lúc nào ngủ không một lúc nào bị bị vọng
or having any distracting thoughts. Only then will we know that after death we will be reborn in the Western Pure Land. This is the Amitabha Sutra. The Infinite Life Sutra describes the realm of Amitabha Buddha and the
cảnh giới Phật a di đà và nói hết về
realms of the highest,
cảnh giới của thượng phẩm Thượng sinh
middle, lower, and even the
Trung phẩm Trung sinh hạ phẩm Hạ sinh và
boundary stages. It explains what kind of practice leads to the boundary stage,
biên Địa đấy ạ và nói tu cái gì thì về
what kind of practice leads to the lower stage, what kind of practice leads to the
biên địa tu cái gì thì về hạ phẩm TU cái
middle stage, and
gì thì về Trung phẩm và tu cái gì Công
what kind of merit leads to the highest stage. It
Đức như thế nào thì được về Thượng phẩng
clearly explains everything.  How to ascend to the realm
nói rõ hết đó và nói lên cái cảnh giới
of Amitabha Buddha and
của đức Phật A di đà như thế nào và cuộc
what life is like in Amitabha Buddha's realm? The
sống ở trên cõi Phật A di đà thế nào và
25th chapter of the Sutra of Infinite Life discusses the three blessings of
nói về chính nhân vãng sinh là phẩm thứ
rebirth: We must possess the
Vãng Sinh tức là chúng ta phải đầy đủ
virtues of compassion, filial piety
các công đức về lòng từ tâm về lòng hiếu
towards parents, respect for
Kính hiếu là đối với cha mẹ Hiếu kính
teachers, compassion, and non-killing. We must also achieve the
đối với Sư trưởng từ tâm bất sát và
precepts and cultivate
người đó phải thành tựu được các giới và
pure faith in
thành tựu được tín tâm thanh tịnh đối
karma and its consequences. Accumulating these
với nhân quả và g sức Tích tập các công
virtues in the 25th chapter of the Sutra of Infinite Life
đức trong phẩm 25 của Kinh Vô Lượng Thọ
is the primary cause of rebirth; one must
đó là chính nhân vãng sinh là anh phải
practice the three blessings of
thực hành được Tam Phước vãng sinh còn
rebirth. Furthermore, the Great Treasure Accumulation Sutra, a very thick sutra about rebirth in the Pure Land, states that for those who wish to be
dày nói về tịnh độ vãng sinh người muốn
reborn in the Western Pure Land, the signs are as follows:
vãng sinh tây phương thì Dấu hiệu thế
3 months prior to
ạ 3 tháng trước đó Tức là cái người được
rebirth, if the person has the aspiration for
vãng sinh ấ mà người ta có cái nguyện
rebirth and practices the dedication of merit,
vãng sinh và người ta thực hành công phu
then 3 months before,
hồi hướng vãng sinh thì 3 tháng trước đó
all the trees in their garden,
tất t cả những cây ở trong vườn nhà họ
even those out of season, will
dù có trái mùa cũng bắt buộc phải ra hoa
continuously bloom and bear fruit.
và ra quả liên tục ra hoa và đơm trái
Those are the signs and realms, dear fellow practitioners.
các quý đạo hữu đấy là dấu hiệu và cảnh
That is, when their minds are pure and they have accumulated enough
giới Đấy tức là tâm họ thanh tịnh đủ
merit to be reborn in the Pure Land, the
công đức vãng sinh thì khiến cho cảnh
external world will be such that whatever flowers they plant
giới bên ngoài là kể cả mình trồng hoa
will flourish and bloom,
gì nó cũng tươi tốt nó cũng ra hoa mình
whatever trees they plant will bear fruit. The Buddha explained this
trồng cây gì nó cũng ra quả Đức Phật nói
very clearly so that people are not deluded or
rất rõ để cho con người Nó không bị mê
confused about being reborn in the
mờ không bị vọng tưởng về cái việc vãng
Western Pure Land. During those three months, there will
sinh Tây Phương thế và trong 3 tháng đó
always be light like the light
thì lúc nào cũng ánh sáng như ánh sáng
of the seven-colored celestial beings shining in the
của chư thiên bảy sắc giao dẹt ở trong
house for three consecutive months. It's
nhà 3 tháng trước 3 tháng liên tục đấy
not that they die first and then
chứ không phải là là cái chuyện là chết
go to the Pure Land. That person
rồi mới mang đến vãng sinh đâu và người
knows the exact time and date of their death, and they
đó biết trước giờ lâm Trung ngày giờ lâm
know it and depart peacefully. And
Trung là người đó biết và tự tại ra đi
for those three months, the house will be filled with the fragrance
và trong nhà từ 3 tháng đó là mùi thơm
of the celestial beings. That's how
của chư thiên đấy có quý đạo hữu ạ Đấy
we know that we have accumulated enough
là chúng ta mới biết rằng chúng ta đủ
merit to be reborn in the Pure Land, dear fellow practitioners. If
công đức vãng sinh các quý đạo hữu ạ Nếu
anyone has the aspiration to be reborn in the Pure Land, and
người nào có nguyện vãng
wants to learn more, they
sinh cho nên ai muốn đọc để tìm hiểu thì
should read the four Sutras: the Sutra of the Accumulation of
hãy đọc bốn Bộ Kinh đó một bộ kinh bảo
Treasures, which speaks of the Pure Land; the Sutra of Contemplation of
tích là bộ kinh nói về Tịnh Độ bộ kinh
Infinite Life, which contains sixteen teachings.  The practice of meditation is
thứ hai là Quán Vô Lượng Thọ có 16 pháp
extremely difficult. Only the
quán quán khó vô cùng chỉ có mỗi pháp
first meditation is the meditation on the rising sun,
quán Đầu tiên là Pháp quán mặt trời mọc
which is easy to practice. But from the second meditation
thì dễ quán còn sang đến pháp quán thứ
onwards, it's impossible to meditate on it; that's already a very
hai trở đi không thể Lào quán được cái
high level of meditation. It's not
đấy thiền định đã cao lắm rồi đấy ạ
easy at all. Even just reading about the sixteen meditation practices is
Không phải dễ đâu mà 16 pháp quán chỉ
difficult, let alone actually practicing them,
đọc còn không hiểu chứ chưa nói gì đến
dear fellow practitioners. I've already said that it's
quán đâu các quý đạo hữu ạ Đã bảo là
not just about having few karmic connections or good roots and merit that leads to rebirth in the Western Pure Land. Therefore, we mistakenly think that simply reciting Buddha's name makes them soft and they will be reborn. It's not just about
vãng sinh không phải hoặc là trong pháp
having a little fragrance or light in that Dharma assembly. That little fragrance, that
hội đấy có chút mùi thơm hay chút ánh
little light—the
đấy ánh sáng một chút
gods and spirits—they can create it. Even evil
đấy chư thiên quỷ thần Họ tạo ra được ạ
spirits can create fragrance and light.
ác quỷ thần họ cũng tạo ra được ánh sáng
So it has to be light for three
cho nên nó phải là ánh sáng trong 3
months, fragrance for three months, as the sutra
tháng mùi thơm trong 3 tháng như kinh đã
says. No one can do that;
bảo tích cái đấy Không ai làm được không
no group can do
có chúng nào làm được cái việc
that in the house of the person who is reborn.
đó ở trong nhà cái người được vãng sinh
Therefore, we must have
đấy nên chúng ta phải có kiến thức chúng
knowledge. With knowledge, first and foremost, we
ta kiến thức thì đầu tiên là chúng ta
must not create negative karma, right?
không bị tạo nghiệp đã phải không Thế
They lack such knowledge, and that
chúng không có kiến thức như thế thì
will create karma.
chúng sẽ tạo nghiệp
The mind of the cyclical contemplation
đấy đó thì tâm chếu hoàn quán Xin giải
explains the first point, and then the mind of the
thích ý thứ nhất như thế và tâm chếu
cyclical contemplation will explain the second point:
hoàn quán sẽ giải thích sang Ý Thứ hai
Is the appearance of the Buddha Amitabha by relatives real or an
a di đà hiện về là thực có hay là ảo
illusion from the mind? Is the deceased's wish
giác từ tâm trí thiết Mong cầu người mất
for rebirth in the Pure Land, or could it be a manifestation of a demon?
được vãng sinh hay có thể do ma Quỳ biến
The family of
hiện ra các cảnh giới không ạ gia đình
the deceased, hearing their daughter say this,
người mất thấy con gái nói như vậy thì
rejoiced, believing the deceased had been
rất hoan hỉ cho rằng người mất đã được
reborn in the Pure Land. Buddhists at the
vãng sinh tịnh độ các phật tử bên Đạo
Pure Land Dharma Center also affirmed that he had been
Tràng Tịnh Độ đ cũng khẳng định ông đã
reborn. Because in our Dharma Center, there are
sinh do trong đạo tràng chúng em có một
some new practitioners with
số phật tử mới tu tập tri kiến còn non
weak understanding, some older, or some who have previously practiced the Pure Land
yếu tuổi đã cao hoặc từng tu tập theo
Dharma, upon hearing
Pháp Môn Tịnh Độ do vậy khi được nghe
this, they may feel joy or
việc này có thể sinh tâm tùy hỉ hoặc cho
believe the deceased has been reborn, or they may have
rằng người mất đã được vãng sinh hoặc
doubts.
cũng có thể đạo hữu Khởi Tâm nghi ngờ
We respectfully request the head of the group to guide
chúng em thành kính mong cô chủ nhiệm à
the Buddhists so that they may have a
chỉ dạy để cho các phật tử có sự hiểu
thorough understanding, avoid losing merit, and avoid losing their
thấu đáo tránh tổn Phước và tránh thối
resolve to practice, thinking that simply reciting
tâm tu tập cho rằng chỉ cần hàng ngày
Amitabha Buddha's name daily or having someone come to them after death is enough.  With the help of the Buddha, one
niệm A Đà Phật hoặc khi mất có người đến
can be reborn in the Pure Land. I
trợ điệm là có thể vãng sinh tịnh độ
respectfully thank the head of the club for her merits.
được ạ em thành kính ch ân công đức trên
Dear fellow practitioners, in the previous section,
nhiệm Kính thưa quý đạo hữu ở phần trên
the Mind-Illuminating Enlightenment Club shared with you
tâm chiếu Hoàn quán đã chia sẻ cho các
about rebirth.
quý đạo hữu về cái việc tái sinh như thế
Regarding seeing Amitabha Buddha,
rồi Thế còn việc mà nhìn thấy Phật a di
remember that the Buddha is impartial.
đà nhớ là Đức phật không thiên vị ai
Let's read the Sutra of Repentance and Eradication of Sins, the
chúng ta hãy đọc quyển kinh sám hối diệt
Adornment of Buddhahood. Next time, the
tội Trang Nghiêm thành Phật đợt tới là
Mind-Illuminating Enlightenment Club will teach the
tâm chiếu Hoàn quán sẽ cho cả câu lạc bộ
entire club about the practice of the Buddha's teachings. When the Buddha emits his light, mountains, rivers, and land become level; hunchbacks are straightened; the blind receive light; the deaf hear. That is, when the Buddha emits his light,
là khi Đức Phật phóng hào quang thì tất
all sentient beings benefit from
cả chúng sinh đều được hưởng cái công
that merit, and everyone can see the Buddha. And
đức đó và ai ai cũng nhìn thấy Phật Còn
when the Buddha emits his light, it's not
khi Đức Phật mà phóng học quang không
just for one
phải chỉ phóng hòa quang đến cho một
person, dear fellow practitioners. As for
mình ai đó đâu các quý đạo hữu ạ Thế còn
our karma preventing us from seeing the
nghiệp của chúng ta không nhìn thấy Đức
Buddha, that's due to our karma, but it's
Phật đó là do nghiệp của chúng ta nhưng
not just for
không phải khi Đức Phật đã phóng hào
one
quang thì phóng hào quang cho một mình
person to
ai đó nhìn
see. And we also encounter
thấy thế và không ít chúng ta cũng gặp
many people suffering from delusions
không ít những người bị bệnh hoang tưởng
or those affected by...  Our hearts are so
hay là những người do cái tâm mình nó
intensely devoted that they create
tha thiết quá cho nên nó sẽ tạo ra những
illusions, seeing things that are very
cái Ảo giác nhìn thấy điều đó rất là
common. Therefore, we shouldn't conclude whether
nhiều cho nên chúng ta không kết luận họ
they saw Amitabha Buddha or not, but
là việc họ nhìn thấy Phật A Di Đà hay
we shouldn't believe it, nor should we
chúng ta không tin điều đó và chúng ta
criticize it. Because we don't know or see it, we don't comment.
cũng không chê bai điều
We don't see or
đó vì chúng ta không biết không thấy cho
hear, nor do we
nên không ý kiến không thấy nghe không
rejoice or feel happy about it. Many phantoms transform into Buddhas.
tùy hỉ vui theo vì ma biến thành Phật
Many of you, dear Dharma friends, have seen
rất nhiều các quý Đạo Hữu có thấy trong
Buddha in your dreams, haven't you? If not, then it
giấc mơ mình cũng nhìn thấy Phật mà phải
's not Buddha
phải không thì có phải là lúc đó là Phật
appearing to us. This is something
hiện đến cho chúng ta đâu Đây là do
we see in our dreams,
chúng ta tự thấy trong giấc mơ chứ không
not reality, dear Dharma friends. So,
phải là sự thật nhá các quý đạo hữu nhá
here we are not discussing
Thế Thế thì ở đây chúng ta không bàn về
this, and we absolutely should not rejoice or feel
việc này và chúng ta tuyệt đối không tùy
happy about it. Never rejoice or feel happy about it.
hỉ vui theo việc đó không bao giờ Tùy hỉ
Dear Dharma friends, you have heard the mind-
như thế các quý Đạo Hữu đã được nghe tâm
body contemplation sharing about the
chếu hoàn quán chia sẻ về cái việc mà
body's stiffness and
thân cứng
softness, and relying on that stiffness and softness to
mềm và y cứ vào thân cứng mềm đó bảo
be reborn in the Western Pure Land. That belongs
được vãng sinh Tây Phương Cái đó thuộc
to wrong views, not right views. Respectfully,
về tà kiến không đúng với chính kiến
dear Dharma friends,
Kính thưa quý đạo
we must remember the Buddha's
hữu chúng ta phải nhớ lời Phật
teachings. When we hear something, we...  There must be
dạy khi nghe điều gì chúng ta phải có
verification; don't believe it without verification.
thẩm sát còn chưa có thẩm sát thì chớ
We must
vội tin nhé chớ vội tin mà chúng ta phải
verify the truth before
có thẩm sát thấy đúng sự thật rồi chúng
we believe it. And as for saying you see
ta mới tin nha Thế còn nói là nhìn thấy
the light of enlightenment, see Amitabha Buddha,
ánh sáng Hảo Quang nhìn thấy Phật a di
see people being reborn in the Pure Land, be careful
đà nhìn thấy người ta vãng sinh cẩn thận
with that statement.  Yes, you must be very careful
với câu nói đó đấy ạ phải rất cẩn thận
with the statement about seeing someone attain
với câu nói là nhìn thấy người ta vãng
rebirth. No one
sinh ạ người ta vãng sinh thì không ai
can see someone attain rebirth except the Buddha and the
nhìn thấy trừ Đức Phật thôi ạ và các bậc
holy monks. No one else can
thánh tăng thôi ạ Chứ còn không ai nhìn
see anyone attain rebirth.
thấy ai vãng sinh gì cả đâu ạ à Kính
Respectfully, dear fellow practitioners, I
thưa quý đạo hữu tâm chiếu Hoàn quán có
read the sutra of Venerable Moggallana.
có đọc bài kinh ngài Mục Kiền niên đấy
He used his divine
ngài phải dùng Thiên
eye to search for his mother in heaven.
Nhãn ngài Tìm Mẹ ở trên trời ngài một
Even a single person like him couldn't find her. He searched
kiền niên còn thế đấy và ngài tìm mẹ
throughout hell but could
ngài suốt cõi địa ngục không thấy ngã
n't find any hungry ghosts. He had to go back to the Buddha to report.
quỷ không thấy ngài phải về Bạch Phật
The Buddha then showed him that
đấy Đức Phật mới chỉ cho ngài biết là mẹ
his mother was on the border between hungry ghosts and
ngài ở giáp biên giữa ngã quỷ và địa
hell. So, you can call her hell or a
ngục cho nên có thể gọi mẹ ngài là địa
hungry ghost. Even with his divine eye,
Quỷ Cũng được mà với con mắt thần thông
a single person like him couldn't see
của ngài một kiền niên còn không thấy
that realm of his mother;
được được cái cảnh giới đó của mẹ mà
only a fully enlightened being could see it. Yet
phải bậc toàn giác mới thấy thế mà chúng
we see people attaining rebirth? It's
ta lại thấy người ta vãng sinh thì quả
truly a matter of mind. I say that
thật là tâm chế Hoàn quán nói rằng lời
statement is a bit too bold. In
nói cũng hơi bị bị mạnh dạn
worldly terms, it's
quá Nếu mà nói theo từ ngoài đời người
called recklessness. Such
ta gọi là ngông cuồng quá nói những câu
statements are quite dangerous, aren't they, dear
nói cũng khá là nguy hiểm đúng không quý
practitioners?  It's quite dangerous if someone who
đạo hữu khá nguy hiểm nếu với một người
fears karma believes in karma;
sợ nhân quả tin nhân quả thì cái lời nói
such words are quite dangerous. Claiming
đó cũng khá là nguy hiểm khẳng định
someone will be reborn in the Pure Land is very dangerous for
người ta vãng sinh khá là nguy hiểm cho
their own karma. If
cái nhân quả của chính mình nhé Nếu mà
those words are considered within the context of Buddhism,
lời nói đó mà được xét về trong đạo Phật
they are lies. They are lies
ấy Nó thuộc vào lời nói dối ạ lời nói
because rebirth in the Western Pure Land is not a
dối vì vãng sinh Tây Phương không phải
joke. It's not about giving
là chuyện đùa đâu ạ nhá không phải trợ
someone a soft or hard recitation of mantras and
niệm cho người ta thấy mềm mềm cứng cứng
then expecting them to be reborn; it's difficult to know for sure.
rồi vãng sinh thật là khó có thể biết
But if someone practices for
được điều đó nhưng nếu như người nào tu
one day and one night, and they say they are single-minded and
một ngày một đêm tôi Nhất Tâm Bất Loạn
undisturbed,
và bả ngày bả đêm tôi Nhất Tâm Bất Loạn
then we can say that
loạn thì mình có thể nói rằng theo cái
if it's true, then they will be
nói của họ nếu được đúng như vậy thì họ
reborn in the Pure Land according to the Buddha's teachings in the
vãng sinh đúng theo lời Phật dạy trong
scriptures. We can't confirm whether they're
kinh nhá Còn mình chưa thể khẳng định họ
telling the truth or lying, but if
nói thật hay nói dối mà mình nói nếu lời
their words are true, then the phenomenon of single-mindedness and
nói của họ là thật thì hiện tượng là một
undisturbed concentration for one to seven days
ngày cho đến 7 ngày Nhất Tâm Bất Loạn
before death is considered
trước khi chết thế này thì sẽ là vãng
rebirth in the Pure Land. That's just according to the scriptures.
sinh nhá đấy mình cứ y kinh mà nói
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause] [
[Vỗ tay]
doctor
nha y